<dashboard showsource="false" script="prettify.js" >
  <label>Help</label>
  <row>
    <panel>
      <html>
      <b>
        <h2>collectd2 App for Splunk Enterprise</h2>
      </b>
      <br/>
        
        <h3>Overview</h3>

      <br/>
        
      The "collectd2 App for Splunk Enterprise" analyzes your collectd metrics.
        <br/>
Those statistics can then be used to find current performance bottlenecks and predict future system load. 
It uses the collectd daemon and http plugin on the client side and the Splunk HTTP Event Collector on the server side to gather data from client machines. 
      <br/>
The application is a complete reimplementation of "collectd App for Splunk Enterprise by Nexinto GmbH" and is using Metric Indexes introduced in Splunk Enterprise 7.0.

     <hr/>
Features:
        
        <ul><li>Analyze system load</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Analyze CPU usage (overall and per core)</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Memory usage (used, cached, buffered, swapped, free memory)</li></ul>
		<ul><li>Storage trending (in-/decrease per host and per partition)</li></ul>
		<ul><li>Storage timeline (Host and Partition usage over time)</li></ul>
		<ul><li>Storage performance (IOPs, Latency, Volume) by host and partition</li></ul>
		<ul><li>Process state (running, sleeping, blocked and zombie processes) over time</li></ul>
		<ul><li>Network throughput and errors (packets/s) by host and interface</li></ul>   
		<ul><li>Metric explorer for custom metrics</li></ul> 


  <br/><br/>
        
	<h3>Installation</h3>
  
  <h4>Server Side</h4>
        
In your Splunk enviroment you need to have Splunk HTTP Event Collector (HEC) up and running. 

Here is a simple setup for lab enviroments

activate HEC in inputs.conf
<pre>
[http]
disabled=0
port=8088
enableSSL=0
dedicatedIoThreads=2
maxThreads = 0
maxSockets = 0
useDeploymentServer=0
</pre>

Configure a HEC input with a token value. Make sure to configure the target index in index key. Ensure that sourcetype is set to collectd_http.

<pre>
[http://collectd]
disabled = 0
sourcetype = collectd_http
token = d8d17157-a4d3-4bb2-1111-222222222222
index = collectd_metrics
indexes = collectd_metrics
</pre>

Configure a metrics index in indexes.conf. Here its name is collectd_metrics.

<pre>
[collectd_metrics]
datatype = metric
# keep data for 60 days
frozenTimePeriodInSecs = 5180000
coldPath = volume:colddb/collectd_metrics/
homePath = volume:hot/collectd_metrics/db
thawedPath = $SPLUNK_DB/collectd_metrics/thaweddb
repFactor = auto
</pre>

<h4>Collectd client Side</h4>

Collectd has to be set up on every client machine. There is no universal forwarder needed on the client itself. Install collectd by using your distribution specific installer.        
<br/><br/>
<pre>
	Debian/Ubuntu : apt-get install collectd -y
</pre>        
        
<br/><br/>        
You need to load the following plugins: cpu, df, disk, interface, load, memory, processes, swap and write_http. Here is an example file for /etc/collectd/collectd.conf.
Make sure to adjust Host “targetfqdnhec” to your Splunk server providing the HEC input and replace the token according to your installation.
<br/><br/>
<pre>Hostname "myclient.fqdn.com"
FQDNLookup false
Interval 60

LoadPlugin syslog

&lt;Plugin syslog&gt;
        LogLevel info
&lt;/Plugin&gt;

LoadPlugin cpu
&lt;Plugin cpu&gt;
  ReportByCpu true
&lt;/Plugin&gt;
LoadPlugin df
LoadPlugin disk
LoadPlugin entropy
LoadPlugin interface
LoadPlugin irq
LoadPlugin load
&lt;Plugin load&gt;
    ReportRelative true
&lt;/Plugin&gt;

LoadPlugin memory
&lt;Plugin memory&gt;
    ValuesAbsolute true
    ValuesPercentage true
&lt;/Plugin&gt;

LoadPlugin processes
LoadPlugin swap
LoadPlugin syslog
LoadPlugin uptime
LoadPlugin users
#LoadPlugin write_graphite

LoadPlugin write_http
&lt;Plugin write_http&gt;
    &lt;Node "node1"&gt;
        URL "https://targetfqdnhec/services/collector/raw"
        Header "Authorization: Splunk d8d17157-a4d3-4bb2-1111-222222222222"
        Format "JSON"
        VerifyPeer false
        VerifyHost false
        Metrics true
        StoreRates true
    &lt;/Node&gt;
&lt;/Plugin&gt;

LoadPlugin logfile
&lt;Plugin logfile&gt;
    LogLevel info
    File "/var/log/collectd.log"
    Timestamp true
    PrintSeverity false
&lt;/Plugin&gt;

</pre>
        
<br/>   
<h3>Data Volume</h3>       
<p>With a reference enviroment we determined a license need of 61MB/host/day when you have an interval of 60 seconds. When you go down to a 5 minutes interval you will need 20% so 12MB/host/day.</p> <p>License needs increased about 240% compared to version1 of the app as Splunk charges 150bytes for every delivered metric.<br/>As a reminder: the collectd graphite data had an average length of ~65 bytes.</p>
<br/>
        
<h3>Client names</h3>       
The client name is determined from collectd.conf hostname entry. Please ensure the hostname is set correctly.

<h3>Hostgroups</h3>       
You can assign hosts to self-configured hostgroups. These hostgroups are used for an inital grouping in the dashboards. A host can be assigned to multiple hostgroups. 
You create and edit hostgroups in the lookups/hostgroups.csv file. 
<br/>
In this example there are 5 hostgroups. The default group "all" contains all hosts. Production contains hosts with "prd" prefix. EC2 instances are prefixed by "ip-".
<pre>
hostgroup,hosts
all,"*"
Production,"prd*"
Integration,"int*"
Development,"dev*"
EC2instances,"ip-*"
</pre>
<br/>   
At the moment you can only use "*" as a wildcard for the hostname - no comma seperated list for multiple entries. 

<br/>
<h3>Dashboard documentation</h3>       

<p>Navigation is the same for every dashboard. In default view every host will be shown. For fast comparison of multiple hosts you can use the "Hosts" dropdown. 
Hostgroups will help you when searching and comparing large amount of hosts.</p>

        <ul><li>CPU load: Displays average and max load of systems for the defined timeframe (default 24h).</li></ul>        
        <ul><li>CPU usage: Displays average and max cpu usage by host. By selecting "Object" you can drill down to every system core.</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Memory: Average and max values for used, free, cached and swapped memory is displayed on host basis.</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Storage trends: Storage increase by host in GB will show storage usage on a host in the defined timeframe. 
		Notice that it will only display hosts and partition where a storage in-/decrease occurs. If you have a partition which is not changing for any kind of 
		reason this partition will not bes displayed.</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Storage timeline: The storage timeline will display a timechart for a host (default with all partitions) and a table displaying the usage on a per day basis. 
		This will help you to see the sum of all usage and which partition is in-/decreasing most.</li></ul>
        <ul><li>Process state: Amount of concurrently running/sleeping/zombie processes and their ratio is displayed. </li></ul>
        <ul><li>Network throughput and errors: Additionally to the host you are able to select a dedicated network interface on the host. 
		If there are no errors for any interface on the host the last panel "error sum by host and interface" will be empty.</li></ul>        
        <ul><li>Metric explorer: Using the metric explorer you can browse all (also custom) metrics which are not used in any dashboard.</li></ul>        

<br/><hr/>
<h3>Feedback</h3>             

If you have feedback, issues or questions please use issue tracker at Github page: http://github.com/Nexinto/collectd.git . 
For direct feedback please contact: andreas@batchworks.de or splunkapps@nexinto.com.  

        <br/><br/>
This app was created by:

<br/> <br/>
Batchworks<br/>
Charlottenstrasse 38<br/>
01099 Dresden
<br/><br/>
Telefon: +49 36202-714901<br/>
<br/><br/>
E-Mail: andreas@batchworks.de<br/>
Internet: www.batchworks.de<br/>

<br/> <br/>
Nexinto GmbH<br/>
Nagelsweg 33-35<br/>
20097 Hamburg
<br/><br/>
Telefon: +49 40-77175-0<br/>
Telefax: +49 40-77175-519
<br/><br/>
E-Mail: splunkapps@nexinto.com<br/>
Internet: www.nexinto.com<br/>
      
      
      
      </html>
    </panel>
  </row>
</dashboard>